Marcel Breuer Papers
Marcel Breuer Papers
- Project records
  - TORIN CORPORATION (VAN NUYS), Van Nuys, CA (1955-1957). Marcel Breuer, Architect; Craig Ellwood, Supervising Architect. [Commercial], (Alternate names: Torrington Manufacturing Co.; Van Nuys Plant; Western Division)
    - Photographs, 17
      - Steel work, construction, exterior view; black and white photographs; 2 (Box 86, Folder 17)
      - View from road [Slide 802], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - View out from terrace [Slide 809], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - View out from terrace [Slide 810], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - View out from terrace [Slide 811], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-14)
  - TORIN CORPORATION, ADMINISTRATION BUILDING, Torrington, CT (1965-1966). Marcel Breuer and Herbert Beckhard, Architects. [Commercial], (Alternate names: General Offices; Torin Corporate Office; Torrington Manufacturing Co.)
    - Drawings, 78
      - Presentation sheets: Plans and elevations, presentation drawings (originals); 4 (Tube 1316)
      - Construction set (Jul-Aug 1965) (Westcott and Mapes, Inc., Architects and Engineers): Structural (Dwg. Nos. 1500-1505), mechanical plot and roof plan (Dwg. No. 2001), plumbing (Dwg. No. 2501), hvac (Dwg. Nos. 2801-2807, 2810), electrical (Dwg. Nos. 3000-3002), working drawings (originals); 18 (Tube 1404)
      - Construction set (5 Aug 1965): Architectural (Dwg. Nos. A1-A17), working drawings (originals); 17 (Tube 1404)
      - Furniture (Mar-May 1966): Dwg. Nos. F1-F4, working drawings (originals); 4 (Tube 1404)
      - Site plan (28 Jun 1965): Dwg. No. 1, design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1405)
      - SK drawings (Dec 1965-Jul 1966): Dwg. Nos. SK1-SK15, working drawings (originals); incomplete; 14 (Tube 1405)
      - Design development drawings and prints (Feb 1965-Jul 1966), design development drawings (originals and reproductions); includes site work and parking studies; 20 (Tube 1405)
    - Published material
      - Torin brochure, 7 copies; features 7 Torin buildings (Box 86, Folder 1)
    - Photographs, 12
      - Cast stone wall panels, finished project, detail; black and white photographs; 5 prints and 1 proof sheet; 6 (Box 86, Folder 2)
      - Construction progress photos, construction, exterior view; black and white photographs; 2 (Box 86, Folder 2)
      - Construction progress photos, construction, interior view; black and white photographs; 2 (Box 86, Folder 2)
      - Northwest façade, finished project, exterior view; black and white photograph; 1 (Box 86, Folder 2)
      - Torrington symbol and partial building elevation, finished project, exterior view; black and white photograph; 1 (Box 86, Folder 2)
  - TORIN CORPORATION, ASSEMBLY PLANT (LAWTON), Lawton, OK (1978-1979). Marcel Breuer and Associates, Architects. [Industrial]
    - Drawings, 13
      - Aerial site photos of Lawton, Oklahoma, site surveys (reproductions); large format; 2 (Tube 1408)
      - Survey, site map and proposed block layout (1978-1979), site surveys (reproductions); 4 (Tube 1408)
      - Design development drawings: Reflected ceiling plan and unnumbered sheet, design development drawings (originals); 2 (Tube 1408)
      - Presentation sheet: Plan, elevations, details, presentation drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1408)
      - Construction set (23 Feb 1979): Dwg. Nos. 1-6, working drawings (originals); 6 (Tube 1408)
  - TORIN CORPORATION, FRANKLIN DRIVE PLANT, Torrington, CT (1978-1979) [Industrial]
    There is little additional information in the collection providing context for this late 1970s design proposal by the Breuer firm. According to an article published in The Register Citizen (Litchfield) on the occasion of the plant's demolition, this was the only of the Torin Corp buildings not designed by Marcel Breuer ("A piece of Torrington history is razed," The Register Citizen, 21 Mar 2010).
    - Drawings, 71
      - Existing conditions: Plans, sections, elevations, presentation drawings (originals); 2 (Tube 1402)
      - Presentation set (1 Aug 1978): Sheet Nos. 1-5, presentation drawings (originals); 5 (Tube 1402)
      - Presentation set: Site plan, plans and elevations, presentation drawings (originals); 3 (Tube 1402)
      - Design development sketches, drawings and prints (Jul 1978-Feb 1979), design development drawings (originals and reproductions); many prints annotated; including loading dock plan, miscellaneous details and draft plans, lighting, cafeteria and food service plans, SK drawings on trace paper, reflected ceiling plans, framing foundation plan; 22 originals and 39 reproductions; 61 (Tube 1402-1403)
  - TORIN CORPORATION, MACHINE DIVISION FACTORY, Torrington, CT (1962-1969). Marcel Breuer and Robert F. Gatje, Architects. [Industrial], (Alternate names: Torrington Factory; Torrington Manufacturing Co.)
    - Drawings, 102
      - Design development sketches, drawings and prints (Aug-Dec 1962), design development drawings (originals and reproductions); includes surveys, site studies, topographic maps, preliminary site work, façade studies, elevations studies, plan studies, wall sections, signs, telephone room, reception area, reflected ceiling plans; 81 (Tube 1406-1407)
      - Structural studies (Feb-Mar 1962), design development drawings (reproductions); 9 (Tube 1407)
      - Structural studies (3 Feb 1962): Sheet Nos. 1-5, design development drawings (reproductions); annotated prints; 5 (Tube 1407)
      - Furnishing layout (Jan-Feb 1963): Dwg. Nos. F1-F3, IF1, working drawings (originals); 4 (Tube 1407)
      - Presentation sheets (circa Oct 1962): Plans and elevations, presentation drawings (originals); 3 (Tube 1407)
    - Project files
      - Correspondence (1968-1969) (Box 86, Folder 3)
    - Photographs, 2
      - Aerial view of building, finished project, exterior view; black and white photograph; 1 (Box 86, Folder 4)
      - Northeast façade, finished project, exterior view; black and white photograph; 1 (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - TORIN CORPORATION, TECHNICAL CENTERS, Torrington, CT (1970-1971, 1983). Marcel Breuer and Herbert Beckhard, Architects (Tech I); BreuerA, Architects (Tech II). [Commercial], (Alternate names: Tech I, Tech II; Torin Tech Centers; Torrington Manufacturing Co.)
    - Drawings, 22
      - Site maps (9 Jan 1962), site surveys (reproductions); 2 (Tube 1401)
      - Serving area (9 Apr 1971): Dwg. No. SK17, working drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1401)
      - Presentation sheet: Plan, presentation drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1401)
      - Kitchen elevations and details (9 Apr 1971) (Herbert Beckhard, Architect), working drawings (reproductions); annotated print; 1 (Tube 1401)
      - Construction set (18 Mar 1970): Architectural (Dwg. Nos. A2, A7, A8, A10), working drawings (reproductions); diazo prints and xerox copies; 7 (Tube 1401)
      - Construction set (4 May 1970): Structural (Dwg. Nos. S1-S2), working drawings (reproductions); multiple copies; 4 (Tube 1401)
      - Construction set (4 May 1970): Site plan and details (L1-L2), working drawings (reproductions); multiple copies; 3 (Tube 1401)
      - Torin Tech II (22 Apr 1983) (MBA): Floor plans and new furnishings (Dwg. No. F1), working drawings (reproductions); 3 (Tube 1401)
    - Photographs, 3
      - Offices, finished project, interior view; black and white photograph; 1 (Box 86, Folder 5)
      - View from northwest, finished project, exterior view; black and white photograph; 1 (Box 86, Folder 5)
      - Window units and split concrete blocks, finished project, detail; black and white photograph; 1 (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - TORRINGTON HIGH SCHOOL, Torrington, CT (1955-1957) (not built). Marcel Breuer and O'Connor & Kilham, Architects; Herbert Beckhard, Associate. [Educational]
    - Drawings, 37
      - Design development sketches and drawings, design development drawings (originals); includes elevation studies, preliminary floor plans, site plans, perspectives; 29 (Tube 1114)
      - Schematic Circulation Diagrams (25 Sep 1957): Teacher, public and student circulation, design development drawings (originals and reproductions); annotated prints; 1 original master sheet and 3 print sheets; 4 (Tube 1114)
      - Presentation sheets: Site plan in broader context, immediate site plan, ground floor plan, presentation drawings (originals); 3 (Tube 1114)
      - Heating system detail (19 Aug 1957) (Slocum and Fuller): Sketch No. HV1, consultant drawings (reproductions); 1 (Tube 1114)
  - TWO DRESSERS FOR MR. AND MRS. H. BECKHARD (1958). Herbert Beckhard. [Projects by Others]
    - Drawings, 1
      - Two dressers for Mr. and Mrs. H. Beckhard (31 Jul 1958): Dwg. No. D, working drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1468)
  - UKRAINIAN STATE THEATER, COMPETITION, Kharkov, Soviet Union (1930-1935) (not built). Marcel Breuer, with the assistance of Gustav Hassenpflug. [Recreational], (Alternate names: Kharkov Theater; Kharkow Theater)
    - Published material, See Professional Papers: Scrapbooks and clippings: Blue scrapbook (1); Professional Papers: Scrapbooks and clippings: Blue scrapbook (2).
    - Photographs, 17
      - Aerial perspective view of theater project, drawings, perspective rendering; black and white photograph; 1 (Oversize 15)
      - Aerial perspective view of theater project [Slide 388], drawings, perspective rendering; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Elevation [Kharkov Theater?], drawings, perspective rendering; glass-plate negative; 1 (Box SL-13, Folder 9)
      - Elevations [Slide no. ANCT8/8974], drawings, multiple drawings; glass-plate negative; 1 (Box SL-13, Folder 6)
      - Interior details, drawings, multiple drawings; black and white photograph; 1 (Box 119, Folder 31)
      - Interior details [Slide no. ANCT10/8974; dup], drawings, multiple drawings; glass-plate negative; 2 (Box SL-13, Folder 7)
      - Perspective and site plan [Slide 115], drawings, multiple drawings; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Plan and longitudinal section [Slide 128], drawings, multiple drawings; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Plan and longitudinal section [Slide no. ANCT2/8974], drawings, multiple drawings; glass-plate negative; 1 (Box SL-13, Folder 1)
      - Plan and longitudinal section [Slide no. ANCT5/8974], drawings, multiple drawings; glass-plate negative; 1 (Box SL-13, Folder 5)
      - Plan and longitudinal section with seat detail, drawings, multiple drawings; black and white photograph; 1 (Box 119, Folder 31)
      - Plan and longitudinal section with seat detail, drawings, multiple drawings; duplicate copy negative; 1 (Box 119, Folder 31)
      - Plan and longitudinal section with seat detail [Slide no. ANCT3/8974], drawings, multiple drawings; glass-plate negative; 1 (Box SL-13, Folder 2)
      - Plan and section [Slide 728], drawings, multiple drawings; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Plans, diagrams, seating details [Slide no. ANCT4/8974], drawings, multiple drawings; duplicate glass-plate negative; 2 (Box SL-13, Folder 3)
  - UNESCO, HEADQUARTERS (PORTE MAILLOT), Paris, France (1952) (not built). Marcel Breuer and Bernard Zehrfuss, Architects; Pier Luigi Nervi, Structural Engineer. [Government], (Alternate names: Porte Maillot; UNESCO I); See also UNESCO, Headquarters (Place de Fontenoy); UNESCO, Headquarters, 4th Building.
    Designs for the original Porte Maillot site were not realized. Material related to the the built design is filed under UNESCO, Headquarters (Place de Fontenoy).
    - Drawings, 1
      - Perspective rendering of Entrance (board mounted), presentation drawings (reproductions); 1 (Oversize 16)
    - Photographs, 4
      - Longitudinal section [Slide 300], drawings, section; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Site plan [Slide 143], drawings, plan; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - View of model from above, model; negative; 1 (Oversize 16)
      - View of model from above [Slide 576], model; color slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
  - UNESCO, HEADQUARTERS (PLACE DE FONTENOY), Paris, France (1954-1958). Marcel Breuer and Bernard Zehrfuss, Architects; Pier Luigi Nervi, Structural Engineer. [Government], (Alternate names: Place de Fontenoy); See also UNESCO, Headquarters (Porte Maillot); UNESCO, Headquarters, 4th Building.
    - Drawings, 250
      - Site plan and sections through Secretariat and conference building, presentation drawings (reproductions); photostats; 4 (Oversize 16)
      - Presentation set: Site plans, plans, sections, elevations, perspectives, diagrams (Sheet Nos. 4, 6-14), presentation drawings (originals and reproductions); with hand coloring; 11 (Tube 268)
      - Design development sketches and drawings, design development drawings (originals); includes project sketches, preliminary site plans, floor plans, design for office cupboard; 67 (Tube 1149)
      - Program organization network diagram, presentation drawings (reproductions); 1 (Tube 1149)
      - Presentation sheets: Site plan, floor plans, presentation drawings (reproductions); multiples of some sheets; FRAGILE; 8 (Tube 1176)
      - Sun control studies and design development drawings for sun shading devices, technical studies/research (originals and reproductions); 35 (Tube 1082)
      - UNESCO Complex (31 May 1954): Architectural (Dwg. Nos. A-1 to A-20), working drawings (reproductions); FRAGILE; 24 (Tube 1085)
      - UNESCO Complex (31 May 1954): Architectural (Dwg. Nos. A-21 to A-45), working drawings (reproductions); FRAGILE; 25 (Tube 1086)
      - UNESCO Complex (31 May 1954): Architectural (Dwg. Nos. A-46 to A-60), working drawings (reproductions); FRAGILE; 18 (Tube 1087)
      - UNESCO Complex (31 May 1954): Architectural (Dwg. Nos. A-61 to A-86), working drawings (reproductions); FRAGILE; 27 (Tube 1088)
      - UNESCO Complex (31 May 1954): Structural (Dwg. Nos. S-1 to S-12); Plan General du 7e Stage (1); Plan General du 1er Stage (1); Plan General du Rez de Chaussée et Amenagements Exterieur (1), working drawings (reproductions); FRAGILE; 15 (Tube 1083)
      - UNESCO Complex (31 May 1954): Structural (Dwg. Nos. S-13 to [S-27]), working drawings (reproductions); FRAGILE; 15 (Tube 1084)
    - Project files
      - Artwork
        - Committee of Art Advisors: Committee documents I (May 1954), Draft Rules of Procedure (CA); in French and English (Box 121, Folder 1)
        - Committee of Art Advisors: Committee documents II (May 1955-Jun 1955), First Session, 16-18 May 1955 (1CCA); in French and English (Box 121, Folder 2)
        - Committee of Art Advisors: Committee documents III (Oct 1955-Nov 1955), Second Session, 3-4 Nov 1955 (2CCA); in French and English (Box 121, Folder 3)
        - Committee of Art Advisors: Committee documents IV (Oct 1956-Nov 1956), Third Session, 1-3 Oct 1956 (3CCA); in French (Box 121, Folder 4)
        - Correspondence: Arp, Jean (Sep 1956-Dec 1956) (Box 121, Folder 5)
        - Correspondence: Bayer, Herbert and Joella (Jan 1956-Dec 1956) (Box 121, Folder 6)
        - Correspondence: Calder, Alexander (June 1955-Nov 1956, Aug 1958) (Box 121, Folder 7)
        - Correspondence: Huxley, Julian (3 Nov 1955), letter/statement "Works of Art in UNESCO House" from former UNESCO Director-General (Box 121, Folder 8)
        - Correspondence: Markelius, Sven (Nov 1956) (Box 121, Folder 9)
        - Correspondence: Miro, Joan (Oct 1956), in French and English (Box 121, Folder 10)
        - Correspondence: Moore, Henry (Nov 1956-Dec 1956), in French and English (Box 121, Folder 11)
        - Correspondence: Noguchi, Isamu (Oct 1955-Aug 1956), in French and English (Box 121, Folder 12)
        - Correspondence: Rogers, Ernesto (Nov 1956) (Box 121, Folder 13)
        - Correspondence: UNESCO Arts and Letters Division/Michel Dard (Jun 1955-Dec 1956), in French and English (Box 121, Folder 14)
        - Correspondence: UNESCO Bureau du Siege/Eugene Callison (Sep 1955-Jul 1956), in French and English (Box 121, Folder 15)
        - Correspondence: UNESCO Committee of Art Advisors (Oct 1955-Dec 1956), A. Manuelides, B. Abramski, M.C. Parra-Perez; in French and English (Box 121, Folder 16)
        - Correspondence: UNESCO Director-General (Aug 1955-Jan 1956), in French and English (Box 121, Folder 17)
        - Miscellaneous notes and correspondence (circa 1956) (Box 121, Folder 18)
      - General correspondence I (1953, 1958), Hans Knoll (1953). Breuer, Nervi, Zehrfuss (1958) (Box 121, Folder 19)
      - Sun control studies
        - Drawing List (25 Sep 1958), H. Seymour Howard, Jr. (architect) (Box 121, Folder 21)
        - Hektograph sheet, "Observations du Vent", mimeograph copy; in French (Box 121, Folder 22)
        - "Sun Control Studies" by Kowalski (19 Dec [1954?]), handwritten, 19 pgs. (Box 121, Folder 23)
        - "Steps in Designing Sunshades" by Kowalski, handwritten, 6 pgs. (Box 121, Folder 24)
        - "Sun Control Studies for the Secretariat Building for UNESCO in Paris" by Seymour Howard (17 Dec 1958), typewritten, 8 pgs. (Box 121, Folder 25)
        - Temperature Chart (Box 121, Folder 26)
    - Published material
      - "Nueva Sede de la UNESCO en Paris," Informes de la Construccion (Feb 1954), photocopy, 8 pgs. (Box 121, Folder 27)
      - "Le Nouveau Siege de L'UNESCO a Paris", tear sheet, pgs. 77-81 (Box 121, Folder 27)
    - Photographs, 494
      - Aerial view of complex in context [Slide 287], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Aerial view of complex in context [Slide 812], finished project, aerial view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - Aerial view of Place de Fontenoy [Slide 338], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Bush-hammering of concrete [Slide 343], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Finished project, 1 color contact sheet and 22 color negatives; 23 (Box 121, Folder 30)
      - Conference building ceiling [Slide 342], finished project, interior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Conference building, conference hall interior [Slide 627], finished project, interior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Conference building, corner of building from above [Slide 298], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Conference building, view along folded wall [Slide 280], finished project, interior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Conference building, view of folded wall [Slide 314], finished project, interior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Conference building, view of sculpture with folded wall [Slide 305], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Conference hall interior [Slide 622], finished project, interior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Conference hall windows [Slide 192], finished project, interior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Conference room [Slide 311], finished project, interior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Construction photos [Slide 323], construction, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Construction photos, construction; black and white photographs; small format; 69 (Box 121, Folder 32-34)
      - Construction photos: Concrete pilotis and stone clad core [Slide 587], construction, interior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Construction photos: Conference building [Slide 756], construction, interior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Construction photos: Conference building folded wall [Slide 286], construction, interior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Construction photos: Conference building roof [Slide 285], construction, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Construction photos: Conference building shell [Slide 586], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Construction photos: Details, construction; black and white photographs; 28 (Box 122, Folder 8)
      - Construction photos: Exterior view [Slide 199], construction, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Construction photos: Exterior views, construction, exterior view; black and white photographs; including aerial site views; 206 (Box 122, Folder 1-7)
      - Construction photos: Folded wall [Slide 255], construction, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Construction photos: Interior views, construction; black and white photographs; 24 (Box 122, Folder 9)
      - Construction photos: Overall site [Slide 282], construction, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Construction photos: Pilotis with formwork [Slide 283], construction, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Construction photos: Secretariat [Slide 292], construction, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Construction photos: Secretariat [Slide 306], construction, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Construction photos: Secretariat frame [Slide 579], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Construction photos: Secretariat frame [Slide 752], construction, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Curved wall with rectangular cutouts, deep concrete beams [Slide 332], finished project, interior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Double-height hall with tapered columns and mezzanine [Slide 341], finished project, interior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Drawings and model photos, drawings and model; black and white photographs; 7 (Box 121, Folder 31)
      - Drawings: Building plan [Slide 574], drawings, plan; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Drawings: Elevations (Dwg. No. A22) [Slide 299], drawings, elevations; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Drawings: Floor plan [Slide 747], drawings, plan; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Drawings: Mechanical diagrams [Slide 309], drawings, systems; color slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Drawings: Mechanical diagrams [Slide 310], drawings, systems; color slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Drawings: Plan du 7th Etage [Slide 201], drawings, plan; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Drawings: Preliminary plans [Slide 308], drawings, plan; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Drawings: Section, perspective, details [Slide 302], drawings, multiple drawings; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Drawings: Section, perspective, details of Secretariat [Slide 303], drawings, multiple drawings; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Drawings: Site plan [Slide 307], drawings, plan; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Elevation detail [Slide 203], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Elevation detail [Slide 205], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Elevation of canopy and partial building elevation [Slide 749], drawings, elevations; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Elevations from plaza [Slide 754], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - End elevation [Slide 154], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Entrance [Slide 158], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Entrance canopy and partial elevation [Slide 750], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Entrance canopy with façade [Slide 336], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Exterior stair and façade [Slide 256], finished project, exterior view; black and white slide; 1 (Box SL-8)
      - Exterior stair and façade of Secretariat [Slide 606], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-9)
      - Exterior view of conference hall windows [Slide 161], finished project, exterior view; color slide; 1 (Box SL-8)